Tammy Rae Carland "I (heart) Amy Carter" Riot Grrrl Collection 1989-1996 MSS.290
Fales Library and Special Collections
Tammy Rae Carland "I (heart) Amy Carter" Riot Grrrl Collection
1992-1996
Fales Library and Special Collections
Carland, Tammy Rae, 1965-
MSS.290
1.6 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Tammy Rae Carland is a Professor at the California College of the Arts where she also chairs the Photography Program. In the 1990's Carland produced a series of fanzines, including I (heart) Amy Carter and Thorn. From 1997-2005 she co-ran Mr. Lady Records and Videos, an independent record label and video art distribution company that was dedicated to the production and distribution of queer and feminist culture. The Collection consists of zines I (heart) Amy Carter, Jailhouse Turn Out, and Thorn; correspondence from friends and fans, mostly requesting copies of the zines; and ephemera. Items in the collection range from 1989-1996.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
Tammy Rae Carland was born in Portland, Maine in 1965. She received her BA from The Evergreen State College, an MFA from UC Irvine, and attended the Whitney Independent Study Program. She is a Professor at the California College of the Arts, where she also chairs the Photography Program. Carland is represented by Silverman Gallery in San Francisco, and primarily works with photography, experimental video and small run publications. Her photographs have been published in several books, including The Passionate Camera; Queer Bodies of Desire, and Lesbian Art in America. Carland's fanzine writing has been republished in A Girl’s Guide to Taking Over the World. She has also published photographs and received reviews of her work in numerous national media.
In the 1990's Carland produced a series of fanzines, including I (heart) Amy Carter and Thorn. She collaborated on the record art for bands Bikini Kill, The Fakes and The Butchies. From 1997-2005 she co-ran Mr. Lady Records and Videos, an independent record label and video art distribution company that was dedicated to the production and distribution of queer and feminist culture.
Provenance
Tammy Rae Carland "I (heart) Amy Carter" Riot Grrrl Collection was donated by Carland to NYU Libraries in 2010.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically within each series. There are three series:
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Zines
Series III: Ephemera
Scope and Content
The Tammy Rae Carland "I (heart) Amy Carter" Riot Grrrl Collection contains materials pertaining to Carland's work on zines in the 1990's, focusing on I (heart) Amy Carter. The collection consists of correspondence from friends and fans, mostly requesting copies of the zines; copies of I (heart) Amy Carter, Jailhouse Turn Out, and Thorn; and ephemera. Items in the collection range from 1992-1996, with the bulk from 1993-1995.
Correspondence; Riot grrrl movement.; Zines.; Feminism.; Punk culture.; Carter, Amy; Martin, Kelly
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Allison, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anonymous, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anonymous, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Aurthur, Kate, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Basilo, Miriam, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beck, J., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Berlin (The Backspace Review), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bill (Seven Warrior Vurgins), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bini, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bodmer, Beth, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Broyles, Susan, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Burdette, Kathy, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Carolyn, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chaisson, John, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chandler, Greg, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cleary, Celeste, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Courtway, Matthew, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Elliot, W.J. (Bill), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fernandes, Joyce, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fodor, Joe, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Frost, Rachel, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - George, Lorna, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Glendening, Kerry, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Gordon (Chow Chow Productions), 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Gould, Larry, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Haddad, Kevin, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hahn, Christine, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hawthorne, M., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Helwig, Maggie, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Herbert, Anne, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hinkley, Bennett, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Holmes, Janet, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Howell, Ben W., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Jacobs, Brian (Desert Moon Periodicals), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Jones, G.B.; Jena, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Kadrey, Richard, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Kennedy, Jeffrey, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Keri, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Kibler, Nathan, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Kische, Reneé, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Knapp, Jennifer, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Landsburg, William, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Lange, Ella, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Larry-Bob, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Lee, Aaron, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Leopold, Blackie G., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Leslie, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Lewis, Sarah, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Lombardi, Laura, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Long, Miles (Suck Don't Blow), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - [Loose Labels and Stickers], Undated (Box 1, Folder 50a)
  - Mack, Bethe, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Malhotra, Kris, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Marx, Glenn, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - McCullock, Kevin, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - McKay, Jim, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Mindich, Jeremy, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Minich, Julie, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Missy, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Mohamadi, Larissa, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Morrow, Diana (Princess Magazine), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Moxham, Tony (Interview Magazine), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Nelson, Christian, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Nikirk, Stephanie, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - O'Leary, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Olson, Jenni, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Parker, Laurel, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Peckham, Perry, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Peterson, Inka, Undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Pinkerton, Brian, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Podraza, Karen F., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Richar, Mark; Gutierrez, Cris (Heat Seeking Publishing), Undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Randall, Alison F., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Roberts, Cameryne, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Roberts, Lori, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Rodgers, Kathleen A. (Rave Magazine), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Romanoff, Sonya, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Sarah, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Schulman, Sarah, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Schwochow, Casey, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Smith, Kevin, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Smith, Troy, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Solestov, M., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Sparks, Asa H., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Speer, Hal, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Staryhorn, Lena Stella, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Stevenson, Alice, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Stoltz, Vernon, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Suelzle, Deb, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Tapper, Cheryl, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Tomassi, Barbara, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Treat, Trinity, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Tuiletufuga, Leilani, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Tyler, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Ward, F., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Weyland, Jocko, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Wien, Leora, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 96)
- Series II: Zines
  - Gateway Kate Productions Catalog, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #1, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #2, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #3, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #4, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #5, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #1 - Master, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #2 - Master, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #3 - Master, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #4 - Master, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter #5 - Master, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - I (heart) Amy Carter - Source clippings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Jailhouse Turn Out #1, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Jailhouse Turn Out #1 - Master, Undated (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Thorn #1, Undated (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Thorn #2, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Thorn #3, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Thorn #4, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Thorn #5, Undated (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Thorn #6, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 116)
- Series III: Ephemera
  - Artwork, Undated (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Pregnant Jimmy Carter postcards, Undated (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Sailor dress, Undated (Box 2)
    General
    This dress was worn in a photograph taken by Tammy Rae Carland, which was used as the album cover for Bikini Kill's Pussy Whipped.